Guide to the Ricardo Sánchez Papers 1968-1995
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Ricardo Sánchez Papers
1968-1995
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Cage 731
Sánchez, Ricardo, 1941-
1.25 Linear Feet of Shelf Space 3 boxes
Sometimes called the "grandfather of Chicano poetry," Ricardo Sánchez was a professor of creative writing and Chicano studies at Washington State University from 1991 until his death in 1995. The collection includes manuscripts (reproductions) and published works. Several of the poetry collections were written and published during Sánchez's tenure at WSU.
Sometimes called the "grandfather of Chicano poetry," Ricardo Sánchez was a professor of creative writing and Chicano studies at Washington State University from 1991 until his death in 1995. He was born March 29, 1941 in El Paso, TX and raised in a neighborhood called "El barrio del diabolo." After serving in the U.S. Army he was convicted of armed robbery and sent to prison. In 1969, he received a Ford Foundation sponsorship as a Frederick Douglass Fellow in Journalism and in 1970 was employed as a staff writer and humanities instructor at the University of Massachusetts, Amherst.
He earned his Ph.D. in American Studies and cultural linguistic theory in 1974, at the Union Graduate School in Cincinnati, Ohio. Subsequently, Dr. Sánchez worked at El Paso Community College (1974), the University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee (1977), and the University of Alaska (1979). From 1977 to 1980 he was an assistant professor at the University of Utah Ethnic Studies Center. At WSU, he was a member of the faculty in both the English Department and the Department of Comparative Cultures, achieving full professorship with tenure in early 1995.
His works include Canto y grito mi liberación (y lloro mis desmadrazgos...): pensamientos, gritos, angustias, orgullos, penumbras poéticas, ensayos, historietas, hechizos almales del son de mi existencia... (The 1995 edition includes poems written during Dr. Sánchez's tenure at WSU); Amerikan journeys = Jornados americanos (1994); Dr. Sanchez' all-you-can-eat poetry buffet, or, Lentils of revolution (1994); Selected Poems (1985); Amsterdam Cantos y Poemas Pistos (1983); Brown Bear and Honey Madness. Alaskan Cruising Poems (1981); and Milhuas Blues and Gritos Nortenos (1978).
Dr. Sánchez died of cancer on September 3, 1995.
[Some biographical information was obtained from: Barceno, Roberto (compiler). "Ricardo Sanchez, Ph.D." (http://www.dr-ricardo-sanchez.com/bio.html).
The collection includes manuscripts (reproductions) and published works. Several of the poetry collections were written and published during Sánchez's tenure at WSU.
The materials are arranged in a single series. They fall into five categories: 1. Materials about Ricardo Sánchez; 2. Photocopies of three Sánchez manuscripts; 3. Publications authored by Sánchez; 4. Publications that include work by Sánchez, such as poetry anthologies and collections; 5. Publications by other authors, owned by (and often inscribed to) Sánchez.
This collection is open and available for research use.
Ricardo Sánchez donated these materials to the Washington State University Libraries in 1992 (MS 1992-42, MS 1992-44, MS 1992-73).
Most of the papers of Ricardo Sánchez are located at the University of Texas at Austin and at Stanford University.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Sánchez, Ricardo, 1941- -- Archives
Literature
  - Sánchez Memorial (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - On Ricardo Sánchez: Marginality and Excess in Chicano Poetry. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper articles on Ricardo Sánchez (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript (photocopy), les Suerostraats of BIG COTULLA.... 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Manuscript (photocopy), Carta/Magda/Carta y otras misivas. (Una Obra Novelistica Epistolaria), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7-10)
  - Manuscript (photocopy), The Furrows of Time's Swathe (a work in progress), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Northwest Cantos Part I. Palousian Poets Press: Moscow, ID, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Brown Bear Honey Madnesses: Alaskan Cruising Poems. Slough Press: Austin, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Amsterdam Cantos y poemas pistos. Place of Herons: Austin, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Milhuas Blues and Gritos Norteños. Spanish-Speaking Outreach Institute, University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Compages. No 18. Autumn 1987. Union of Left Writers: San Francisco, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rio Grande Review. Spring-Summer 1992. Volume 11, number 2. University of Texas at El Paso (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - New Blood Magazine. Number 6. New Blood Press: Boulder, circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Festival Flor Y Canto II. An Anthology of Chicano Literature. Pajarito Publications: Albuquerque, circa 1979 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - International Journal of Art, Science &Philosophy. Volume III, numbers 1and 2. Pax Cultura Press: Texas, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "Los Tejanos." Special issue. Revista Chicano-Riqueña. Año VIII. Autumn 1980. Number 3 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Mind Spew. Cerebral Spillings: An Anthology of Experiences. Malcontent Press: Moscow, ID, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Nosotros. June 1972. Volume 2, number 3. El Paso, TX (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Caracol. La revista de la raza (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - November 1977; volume 4, number 3
    - January 1978; volume 4, number 5
    - February 1978; volume 4, number 6
    - April 1978; volume 4, number 8
    - July 1978; volume 4, number 11
    - August 1978; volume 4, number 12
    - July-August 1979; volume 5, numbers 11 and 12
  - Hispano Americano. Volume LXXIV, number 1920. 1979 February 19 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - La Luz (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Volume 7, number 1, 1978
    - Volume 8, number 2, 1979
  - Nuestro (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
    - Volume 1, number 7, 1977 October
    - Volume 1, number 9, 1977 December.
    - Volume 2, number 1, 1978 January
    - Volume 2, number 3, 1978 March
    - Volume 2, number 4, 1978 April
    - Volume 3, number 7, 1979 September
    - Volume 3, number 12, 1980 January-February
  - Tiempo. Volume LXX, number 1808. 1976 December 27 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - ¡A Mi Que! Jose Montalvo. With foreword by Sánchez. Raza Cosmica: San Antonio, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Papel De Estraza. Number 113. 1985 May. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Nonstop. Marion Winik. Cedar Rock Press: New Braunfels, TX, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - El Politico. José Angel Gutiérrez. El Politico: the Mexican American Official. Míctla Publications: El Paso, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Chicanos. Our Background and our Pride. Nephtalí De León. Trucha Publications, Inc.: Lubbock, TX, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - I will catch the Sun. Nephtalí De León. Trucha Publications: Lubbock, TX, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - "The Mexican American. A New Focus on Opportunity." Testimony Presented at the Cabinet Committee Hearings on Mexican American Affairs. El Paso, TX. 1967 October 26-28. U.S. Government Printing Office: 1968 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - 1916 Villa Raid! Bill Rakocy. Bravo Press: El Paso, TX. 1991 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Great Missions of the Southwest. Bill Rakocy. El Paso Museum of Art. 1987 September (Box 3, Folder 38)